Finding Aid for Loren Barritt papers, 1963-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Loren Barritt papers 1963-2000
Barritt, Loren.
9786 Aa 2
Professor in the University of Michigan School of Education. Files include correspondence with colleagues, papers presented at professional meetings, research proposals and reports, grant and fellowship applications, materials related to committees on which Barritt served, and newsletters. The collection documents his research interests in educational testing and measurement, language development and testing, European (particularly Dutch) approaches to education and research, and educational psychology.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4.5 linear feet
The collection was donated by Loren S. Barritt (donor no. 6935 ) in 1996 and 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Loren Barritt has enjoyed a long and productive career in education. He received a B.A. degree in English from Blackburn College in 1958. He received an M.A. degree in Guidance and Counseling in 1961 and a Ph.D. in Educational Psychology in 1964 from Indiana University School of Education. At the University of Michigan School of Education Barritt served as an assistant professor from 1964 to 1968 and associate professor from 1968 to 1973. Since 1973, he has been a professor.
Barritt's research interests have evolved through the years. His dissertation in 1964 concerned the predictive validity of educational tests. In 1966 he joined the University of Michigan Center for Research on Language and Language Behavior. From 1966 to 1970 he conducted research on language testing for normal and retarded children.
European approaches to education and research held strong appeal for Barritt. In the first of four sabbatical leaves to study abroad, he spent the early months of 1970 as a visiting scholar at the Institute for the Scientific Study of Education at the University of Geneva, where he attended lectures by Jean Piaget. Barritt spent the 1973-74 academic year as a Senior Fulbright Lecturer at the University of Utrecht. Back at the University of Michigan in 1974, Barritt established the Phenomenology Seminar, which in 1981 was renamed the Human Science Research Association meeting. The seminar brought together scholars interested in phenomenological approaches to educational research, which concentrates on a dialogue between study subjects and researchers and encourages participation in the lives of the subjects. He returned to the Netherlands in 1978-79 with a Visitors Grant from the Netherlands Institute for Basic Research to write a monograph on "Researching Educational Practice," and in 1985-86 with a research grant from the Dutch Ministry of Education to study a Dutch elementary school.
Barritt served as the chair of the University of Michigan School of Education Program in Curriculum, Teaching and Psychological Studies from 1986 to 1990. In addition, he has served on numerous university committees. Throughout his career, Barritt has been an active member of many professional associations, including the American Educational Research Association, the National Council on Measurements in Education, and the Human Science Research Association, the North Dakota Study Group on Evaluation, and the American Anthropological Association.
The papers of Loren Barritt consist primarily of materials related to his career as a professor of education at the University of Michigan School of Education from 1964 to 2000. Records include correspondence with colleagues, papers presented at professional meetings, research proposals and reports, grant and fellowship applications, materials related to committees on which Barritt served, and newsletters. They document his research interests in educational testing and measurement, language development and testing, European (particularly Dutch) approaches to education and research, and educational psychology. Six series make up the collection: Correspondence, Professional Activities, Course Materials, Research, Grant and Fellowship Applications, and Committee Work.
Subjects:
Barritt, Loren.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Language and Language Behavior.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; Rijksuniversiteit te Utrecht. Instituut voor Pedagogische en Androgogische Wetenschappen.; Education--United States.; Education--Netherlands.; Educational psychology.; Educational tests and measurements.; Language and education.; Learning, Psychology of.; Phenomenological psychology.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Correspondence 1972-1999
  The Correspondence series documents Barritt's professional life at the University of Michigan School of Education and his work in the Netherlands, 1972-1999. The years 1981-1985 are not documented. The series includes private correspondence that Barritt had with other professors and researchers in educational science. Worth noticing are the many scientific articles sent to Barritt by colleagues, along with invitations to professional meetings.
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Holland
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - 1986 (Program in Curriculum, Teaching and Psychological Studies) (Box 1)
  - 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Program in Curriculum, Teaching and Psychological Studies) (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1988 (Box 1)
  - May-June-1988 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
  - January-May 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - 1997-1999 (Box 2)
- Course Material 1965-1999
  The Course Material series represents the core and the most interesting part of Barritt's papers. Extending from 1965 to 1999, the series spans the totality of his teaching career, with the bulk covering the late eighties and the nineties. Course material consists mainly of outlines describing the aims of the course, schedules and programs, and course handouts, bibliographies, excerpts and articles. Barritt used to take notes during his courses about the topics discussed, as well as students' reactions and remarks. Best represented courses are Education 391 (Educational Psychology and Human Development), 725/726 (Human Science approaches to Educational Research) and 794 (Methods of Educational Research).
  - Master of Arts in Education with Certification (MAC)
    - Correspondence, outlines, handwritten notes, students' evaluations 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Handouts 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Outlines, handwritten notes 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Students' lists, motivations, evaluations 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Education 391-Educational Psychology and Human Development
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Education 607-Educational Measurement 1965-1982 (Box 2)
  - Education 612-Seminar in Learning 1968-1975 (Box 2)
  - Education 642-Development of Language and Thought 1969-1982 (Box 2)
  - Education 686/687-Research in Human Science 1981-1987 (Box 2)
  - Education 695-Research in Education
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Education 699-Alternatives in Research with children 1975-1981, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Education 700-Growth self 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Education 701-Psychology of Learning 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - Education 725/726-Human Science approaches to Educational Research
    - Outlines, bibliographies, excerpts and articles 1980-1995 (Box 3)
    - Students' works
      - 1987-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1993 (Box 3)
      - 1994 (Box 3)
  - Education 794-Methods of Educational Research
    - Outlines, bibliographies 1995-1997 (Box 3)
    - Students' works
      - 1995 (Box 3)
      - 1996 (Box 3)
  - Education 812-Themes in the Development of Educational Psychology 1975-1976, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Education 882-Research in Interpersonal Relations 1980 (Box 3)
- Research 1963-2000
  The third series, Research consists of research proposals, data, and reports from the early part of Barritt's career. Projects included a 1963 Transformation Study to explore the relationship between grammatical structure, learning and attention; a 1966-68 Infant Vocalization Study to observe and record an infant's acquisition of language; a 1968 TV Dialect Study to determine whether inner-city African-American children recalled TV jingles accurately or with a dialect; a 1969 TV Violence Study to discover whether children could distinguish between what happens on television and what happens in real life; and a 1983-85 Basic Writer Study to analyze "basic students" and their teachers in Ann Arbor area high schools.
  Other research related to several high school reform projects. With some of his colleagues, Barritt was member of the Informal Research Group (IRG), whose goal was the implementation and the development of such a reform project. The reflections of IRG members led to the House One School project, conducted between 1990 and 1992. This experiment, that took place at the Huron High School, proposed an alternative curriculum promoting pupils' initiative and imagination. In the High School Reform Projects files can be found descriptive booklets, reports about the implementation of the program and the results achieved, along with correspondence with other people involved in the project. Furthermore, Barritt collected many newspapers articles, for the House One School proved to be a somewhat controversial operation. Similar documents are to be found about a second High School reform project, called the New School Program, which was developed beginning in 1996. The initiatives of the Informal Research Group were not isolated ones, and Barritt also investigated other projects within Michigan and the United States, such as the Model High School Program.
  - Transformation Study 1963 (Box 4)
  - Infant Vocalization Study 1966-1968 (Box 4)
  - TV Dialect Study 1968 (Box 4)
  - TV Violence Study 1969 (Box 4)
  - Basic Writer Study 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - High School Reform Projects
    - Informal Research group's proposals and meetings 1983-1989 (Box 4)
    - House One School Program
      - Correspondence, project's presentations, meetings minutes, schedules, reports 1990-1992 (Box 4)
      - Newspapers clippings 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - New School Program
      - Correspondence, project's presentations 1996-1997 (Box 4)
      - Evaluation report of the first three years 1996-1999, 2000 (Box 4)
      - Program description and Curriculum overview 1999 (Box 4)
      - Overview of the New School Pilot Program August 1999, January 2000 (2 videotapes: VHS) (Box 4)
    - Other projects in the USA
      - Studies, articles 1988-1992 (Box 4)
      - Model High School Program 1990-1993 (Box 4)
- Professional Activities 1965-1988
  Professional Activities include some correspondence, papers presented at professional meetings, and the Human Sciences Newsletter, a product of the Phenomenology Seminar at the University of Michigan begun in 1974 by Barritt. The series especially documents Barritt's involvement in professional organizations such as the American Educational Research Association (AERA), the National Council on Measurements in Education (NCME), and the Human Science Research Association, the North Dakota Study Group on Evaluation, and the American Anthropological Association.
  - 1965-1983 (Box 5)
  - 1984-1988 (Box 5)
  - Human Sciences Newsletter. 1982-1987 (Box 5)
  - Project Community 1982 (Box 5)
- Grant and Fellowship Applications 1985-1987
  Grant and Fellowship Files include unsuccessful applications for a Fulbright grant, a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation fellowship, and a W. W. Kellogg Foundation/Presidential Initiatives Fund grant.
  - Fulbright Proposal 1985 (Box 5)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship Proposal 1987 (Box 5)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation/Presidential Initiatives Fund Application 1987 (Box 5)
- Committee Work 1980-1984
  Committee Work consists of records relating to Barritt's service on several University of Michigan committees and task forces.
  - University of Michigan. School of Education. Core Committee 1982 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan. School of Education. Curriculum Task Force Report 1984, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan. English and Education Program Committee 1980-1982 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan. Netherlands Area Studies Proposal 1982
  - University of Michigan. School of Education. Study for Human Sciences Approaches Proposal 1982